Is crypto dead?
>> Capital, technology, and culture. And if
you look at those three things, I think
they're good ways to identify whether or
not you continue to see the momentum
gives you then a signal to say, is this
something that you want to continue
investing in or looking at to invest in
or considering to to enter, right? What
is a good predictor of uh innovation,
adoption? It boils down to three things.
in my [music] face. She's the queen of
the game. Stacking crypto like it's her
claim the fame. If you want success,
then [music] take a look away.
All right, everybody. Our guest today,
Michael Laauo. He's a chairman of
Consensus, one of the I would say best
crypto events in the world, and I'm
really excited about it. He spent over
decades navigating global finance and
crypto from the inside from JP Morgan,
CoinDesk, Bullish, and many, many more.
And today we're going to talk about how
institutions are navigating this really
volatile market and are we going to make
money in 2026 in crypto. Michael,
>> I think it's going to be an exciting
year ahead.
>> Yeah. Okay. Well, let's let's talk about
the market past one-year return. Silver
has been up 171%, gold 76%, copper 36,
and crypto is down 24%. So people are
like, is crypto dead?
>> Look, I I don't I don't think it's uh
it's wise to kind of look at a single
short window to kind of decide what you
want to do long term. You know, I've
been in the space now for about six
years, and there's been a number of
cycles that have happened within that
short period of time. I can't say that
I've seen as many cycles in a short
period of time as I have when I was tra
traditionally uh in equities but I do
think that if you look at some of the
underlying things and I I think I
probably want to approach this a little
bit from an ecosystem perspective as
well um I think what's most interesting
about this particular space is that it's
kind of like one of those places that
has a unique convergence of capital
technology and culture and if you look
at those three things I think they're
good ways to identify whether whether or
not you continue to see the momentum
that gives you then a signal to say is
this something that you want to continue
investing in or looking at to invest in
or considering to to enter right from a
capital perspective I think it's been
very clear that over the last 2 years
you've seen more and more of that
institutional capital being deployed you
started to see more institutionalized
products enter the market you saw that
the effectively the the joining up of
traditional equity markets and also you
know the the you know digital assets
markets with the form of these ETFs,
right? And so you're starting to see
again capital that is being deployed in
ways that weren't being deployed just
two years ago. I think the other part of
it is the technology, right? If you
think about how technology is being
built and adopted over time, I'd say
that it's just continued to pick up
momentum. I think one of the things that
I look at quite a bit are what are the
projects that people are building, what
are the problems that people are trying
to solve for. And I think you know the
the whole industry has moved towards
things that matter right the ability for
people to be able to have a way to
transmit to be able to pay to be able to
do things in a faster cheaper more
accessible manner stable coins is is an
incredible focus of energy and time of
the whole industry this past year and I
think that again from a technology
perspective it kind of shows to me that
there's still a very strong underlying
momentum towards the right problems
right that are being solved and this
technology taking further root and the
final piece is the cultural aspect right
I think that is a community sense
continues to strengthen I do think that
builders are still coming together I
think people are still doing a lot of
partnerships together and to me that's
very promising so you know I think if
you kind of take a step back and look at
it from this kind of more ecosystem
builder perspective I think there's a
lot of really healthy signs that the EOS
ecosystem continues to grow and that we
continue to move forward towards the
right things in the same direction as we
have been for for a while now. Um, and
at the same time, hopefully people that
are investing and that are spending time
thinking about markets start to
understand that as a way to factor into
how they think about the ways that they
invest because at the end of the day,
investment is a multiffactor decision,
right? This is just one of the the main
factors that I think matter. Um, but
there are other things that are kind of
outside of the control of our industry,
but also outside the control um of of us
in general. So, I think to a certain
degree, it's trying to look for things
that are a bit more fundamental. And I'd
say that from that perspective, I still
think that this is a place where there's
an incredible opportunity uh for more
growth.
AWS, Crypto.com Capital, Kronos,
HSBC, JP Morgan, Kexus, UBS, Salana
Foundation, Oros Ventures. First,
You know, when you think about how
markets work, um, there are a lot of
factor factors and there's a lot of
different things that are happening and
I think one thing that's very clear is
that what happens within the crypto
world is not in isolation to the macro
um kind of setting and I think it's
important to know that that's a good
thing because it means that we've become
more mainstream as an industry as an
asset class that there is for example uh
a bigger picture that we're that we're
being a part of right so looking at
markets I think it's important that you
understand kind of where you are um how
you approach you know risk how do you
approach um the macro setting as well as
what's happening within the industry
>> so your thesis hasn't changed
>> for me I mean I I kind of joined this
industry six years ago um I'm still very
excited about it I don't think that's
changed very much I think I certainly
gotten older being [laughter] in the
market for six years uh but yeah no it's
it's it's something where I I feel very
strongly uh conviction wise about what
the technology can
When you talk about technology, can you
elaborate a little more on what are the,
you know, things that excite you the
most? Is it stable coin uh prediction
market? What are what are signals? And
what are noises?
>> If I were to summarize kind of what is a
good predictor of uh innovation,
adoption, it boils down to three things.
Is it faster? Is it cheaper? Is it more
accessible? And I think what we found
with stable coins is that it's answered
that for a couple of different use
cases. You know for some people um it's
a question of transmitting value and is
it faster and cheaper more accessible
than going to a bank going using you
know another more traditional route for
some parts of the world yes it is way
faster and way cheaper right and then I
went to another use case which is quite
funny because this is not usually what
you talk about is I went to some places
in the world where the US dollar was the
store of value that people have been
using for a long time And all of a
sudden, stable coins became a faster,
cheaper, more accessible way of getting
to the store of value. So like we don't
really talk about stable coins as as a
store of value thing. We usually use
that in the context of Bitcoin, but in
this situation, that's actually
something that it's solved for much
faster and better and cheaper. And so I
think there's there's interesting
applications stable coins have done that
I feel are very very um
unique and and kind of quite cool. Uh
and then the other side of it is also I
think there's a lot of new things that
are happening around the layer 1, layer
two side of things, right? I think one
is just it's faster. You know, we we've
always been talking about how fast can
blockchains work to be able to do the
kind of um transactions that we're
thinking about for more bigger financial
um uh systems. But also, I'd say that
there's also now a large focus on
privacy, which I think is very
important. You know, I think there's a
little bit of this idea of, you know,
blockchain for a long time was talking
about anonymity and kind of like I own
for example a wallet address and you
know maybe you disclose, maybe you
don't, doesn't matter, but your actions
on chain are still very transparent,
right? And that's kind of where for
example when you think about how people
are allocating um or investing in the
space privacy in your actions is also
quite important and your ability to
decide on how to think about that is
also very important. So there's a lot of
newer projects that have come to the
forefront or or existing projects that
are now focusing on privacy more. So
that's another key area that I think has
emerged over the last 12 months that I
think are getting a lot of people
excited and could be enabling to a lot
of different things.
>> We're talking about big pictures and
institutions. They're obviously looking
at, you know, a different scale, but for
in retail investors, they want to know,
I think they want to know how fast do I
need the blockchain to be like they're
they're not really seeing the back end,
right? Well, you guys are talking about
how fast it is, how cool it is, but in
reality, they want to know if there's a
chance for them to make money or, you
know, make a good investment. Is that
chance getting slimmer with all these
institutional players getting involved?
>> The individual retail interaction with
this technology in an ideal world to me
is almost invisible that you don't even
realize that this is happening in in in
in the space. Like there's this one
example of a company that I know of who
is doing like traditional payments and
if you were to use them, you'd think
it's just general payments, but they're
just using stable coins in the back to
transfer things back and forth to make
it all work. And so for you as a retail
user, you don't even know that there's
blockchain being involved in this. And I
think the idea of having these things
solved for so that they can you know
allow companies to provide better
services and better products to retail
users is I think where we're going to
find more and more of the application
really you know rubber hitting the road
and I think that's also where it's going
to be most beneficial because if you can
bring cost down that means the services
that retail people users are asking for
uh become cheaper right and so I do
think that there's an element of that
people should keep in mind that this is
not just simply an institution
conversation that has no effect on
retail.
>> Is there anything that might happen in
the next let's say 6 to 12 months that
would change your mind?
>> I mean the truth is like it's so hard in
our industry to kind of you know predict
6 12 months what's going to happen.
>> Oh yeah.
>> I mean I've tried that a couple times
and was wrong every single [laughter]
time. So I mean the one thing I can say
again is a little bit of this I know it
doesn't sound like a long time but six
years kind of being in this industry um
has kind of only for me at least kind of
furthered my conviction around kind of
the underlying technology and that you
know there are different seasons to this
industry. There's different flavors to
kind of what's happening right now. Um,
but that hasn't changed, you know, uh,
what I focus on, what I am interested
in, kind of where I spend my time and
attention.
>> It sounds like you don't check Bitcoin
price every morning.
>> You kind of have to look at it every now
[laughter] and then, right? I think if
if all you're doing is looking at price,
then, you know, you're going to be
constantly on a roller coaster. uh if
you're looking at that together with
other factors and that's kind of why I
started off with this idea of what are
some of those more fundamental factors
that I think about as you know kind of
more of an ecosystem perspective that I
think are healthy signs of a of a strong
ecosystem to me it makes me feel a lot
less um uh it dampens the effect of the
roller coaster if that makes sense.
>> You live in Hong Kong right?
>> Yeah.
>> Are you from there? So, a lot of family
roots from Hong Kong. Um, but I was born
in Canada and moved here 18 years ago.
So,
>> to me, Hong Kong is home. This is where
um a city that I love. And yeah, no,
it's it's it's been a fascinating place
uh to be a part of. I
>> I think the recent years we've seen
other financial powerhouses coming like
Singapore, UAE, they're all trying to
compete in this, you know, crypto
industry, the crypto hub. From what you
are seeing in Hong Kong, you think the
rest of the world actually recognize how
important Hong Kong is in crypto or is
it just, you know, within Asia we
recognize that?
>> Yeah, I'd say that there's it's
interesting because it it's a little bit
based on who you ask and I'll kind of
put it just in two very simple
categories. Those who are in Asia and
those who are not in Asia.
>> Yeah. For those who are in Asia, I think
who have an understanding of kind of how
markets work around here, I think there
is a recognition that there are certain
centers of finance that matter quite a
bit and that Hong Kong is definitely one
of them. I think when you're, you know,
not in Asia, you tend to forget that
there's a significant part of capital
flows that are coming from this area of
the world and that Hong Kong stands in
them. So, for example, when you think
about traditional markets, Hong Kong
ranked as the number one global IPO
market last year, right? Most people
probably don't realize that, but that's
actually like if you just look at the
data, that's kind of what it is.
>> And so, when you're thinking about TRFI,
Hong Kong already maintains a very
significant position in the global
traditional financial system. And so
when you think about crypto and
blockchain and digital assets, like one
of the biggest themes is this idea of
tradi and crypto converging, right? And
if you think that that's one of the big
themes that matters, then it matters
where it happens. And if it's happening
in Hong Kong, where it's already one of
the top global hub financial hubs in the
world,
>> then there's a level of significance
around that. And I think that's been
quite interesting to see. I think the
other thing that's worth noting is that
and people miss when you're outside of
Asia is also the fact that Asia has been
in this kind of regulatory clarity
journey a lot longer than most people
have right like I was explain
[clears throat]
>> yeah so I was in Thailand just you know
uh two weeks ago uh together with with a
partner to talk about consensus and my
the partner that I was working with
reminded me that hey Thailand issued
their first set of policies and
regulations related to virtual assets
back in 2018. 18,
>> right? And then you think about
Singapore, it's like since 201920,
>> you know, if you go around the region,
you'll realize that most people have
started regulating this thing several
years ago, whereas the clarity that
we're starting to see from the US is
just within the last, you know, year and
a half. So, I think people from outside
of Asia tend to forget that there's been
a lot of uh time and energy that has
been put into this. And even within Hong
Kong, it was in October of 2022 that the
government put out a policy statement
that says that Hong Kong wants to be a
web three hub. And it's been moving in
that direction since. And it's provided
regulations for what we call virtual
asset trading platform. So those are
like exchanges provided now also
regulations for stable coins. A lot of
these things moving a lot faster than
what we've seen in some other parts of
the world outside of Asia. And so I
think that's also another key thing that
people tend to forget is that this
journey has been pretty consistent and
has been there for a while. And I think
that's also again kind of creating some
pretty cool foundations for building
businesses and projects and technology
in the region.
>> When I think of Hong Kong, I imagine old
money and people say old money are, you
know, a little more conservative
compared to let's say tech focused
countries or regions. Does that affect
how you know legislations move forward
in Hong Kong or just the mentality in
general? Is it different?
>> I'd say that with Hong Kong there's a
mix. There's certainly a lot of old
money that is still here. But the one
thing you got to remember is that Hong
Kong has has basically in my opinion
been built by a lot of entrepreneurs and
a lot of really good you know policy
support around that. And I think that
that entrepreneurship also stems into
some of the more newer technologies and
and a lot of people, you know, have
seen, for example, the rise of, for
example, Chinese internet over the last
decade and a half. And a lot of that
also comes down over here to Hong Kong.
And so the capital here, I think, comes
from both old and new. And I'd say that
there is there is a reflection of that
>> that you're seeing here because Hong
Kong, for example, before we even start
talking about blockchain and digital
assets, fintech has been a core part of
the the conversation here for a while,
right? That's kind of the precursor to
what we're what we're talking about. And
that's also been something where Hong
Kong has been at the forefront of and
has been pushing forward. And you'd see,
for example, again going back a little
bit, traditional banks offering really
interesting digital solutions for what
they were doing back in 2010s. So I
don't think it's just old money. I think
it is a mix. But I do think that to your
point, like the one thing that I've
noticed about how I guess policy and
regulation uh kind of gets rolled out
here in Hong Kong is that they're very
uh measured and they're very considerate
and and they spend a lot of time
studying and understanding so that when
they do something, they do something
meaningfully, but they also do something
uh having considered a lot of things.
And so the pace of it is something that
also reflects that too. And I think that
that's also part of what you kind of see
in terms of the journey and how it's
unfolded over the last couple years.
>> I think that's in the culture as well.
You know, the Asian culture, they are a
lot more careful when it comes to things
and they evaluate, you know, they take
their time. And I assume, you know, you
talk to a lot of founders from the US,
they probably want to, you know, get
into the Asian markets, but Asia is a
whole different beast. Like it's so
different. Um, what are the questions
they're asking and how are they
approaching this?
>> Yeah. So I I'll tell you one of the
things that um I really really wanted to
push when we started uh consensus Hong
Kong was that Hong Kong is kind of
uniquely 4 hours [snorts] flight
distance from pretty much the entire
region of Asia. Right? So the intention
was how can we make this as a gateway to
the region so that when people are
flying over from the US or Canada or you
know Europe or or Middle East that
they're able to get a pulse of what's
happening across the region. And I think
that what we found is that most people
again find Asia um just a lot of ground
to cover because you have different sets
of rules. you have different sets of you
know societies and cultures and uh
different journeys in terms of their
adoptions uh of the technology that it
takes a lot of time to really understand
what's going on and also it's important
to figure out who are the right sources
to understand this from right like who
are the authoritative voices talking
about what's going on and so I think
those are some of the bigger challenges
yeah that most people have understanding
Asia it takes time it takes energy um
and that's kind of why we thought, hey,
this could be a really good opportunity
for us to bring together leading
authorities of what's happening in these
different markets and these different
geographies to Hong Kong. So, you have a
convenient way to be able to meet them
and then decide, hey, you know what?
Realizing maybe I need to do more stuff
in Korea. I should do a deep dive into
Korea and then, you know, you should go
to, you know, our good partners over at
Korea Blockchain Week later on in the
year to find out more about what's going
on. So I think there's there's elements
of that discovery and energy that you
need to have if you want to understand
what's happening around Asia. If you're
looking at um capital flows, Asia is
also a powerhouse when I think about
where capital is being uh formed,
raised, deployed, invested. And so
again, if you're in kind of the
financial world, it's really important
that you are active in this region,
right? The fact that Asia as a region
has you know various different
countries, various different regulators
etc means that there's going to be
friction across uh different markets as
well and that's where we've seen a lot
of people actually entering in the space
to say hey look we've got some
interesting solutions to help with that
crossborder whether that's trade
remittances payments whatever it might
be and I think that again think about
demographics think about capital flows
think about opportunities like that's I
think uniquely large in Asia versus some
of the other regions of the world.
>> I love that. I I I think Asia is really
really important. But I just want to
make sure you know people see it that
way too. [laughter]
>> Yeah.
>> And coming from you, it's very
reassuring. Okay, let's talk about
consensus. What are you most excited
about? Who do you want to listen to?
Any crazy stories prepping for this
event? The first one was that we were
very surprised at how um wellreceived
the first inaugural consensus was last
year.
>> It was the very first time bring
consensus to Hong Kong at this scale and
we ended up selling out 10,000 people,
right? So like that was a really great
first time around. So you know one of
the big questions is how do we continue
to grow it? How do we continue to make
it attractive and hopefully you know
bring more people over this time around?
So in terms of what I'm excited about,
one is I think we've continued to stick
to this vision of just really high
quality content at scale
>> and really being I guess the place that
brings the industry together. I think
one thing I'm particularly proud about
this year for Consensus Hong Kong is
that we've brought in a lot of the
founders and senior management of a lot
of layer ones all into the same place,
right? Whether that's Salana or that's
Cardano or that's Ethereum or whatever.
like we've we've we've brought them
here. And so for somebody who wants to
understand the industry or want to
understand everything to do with
programmable blockchains like we have we
are the place to bring the most
important people of those different
chains together. I think that's one
thing that's very exciting. The second
thing is that and so we've also expanded
the content this year to also focus on
things like what's happening in AI,
what's happening with regards to AI and
blockchain technology coming together.
So we're excited about that. I think the
other thing that I'm quite excited about
is again kind of the public support that
we're getting um from the government
around this conference. So for example,
last year we had the financial secretary
of Hong Kong give the you know opening
keynote. He's coming back again in
person to give a keynote but actually
the opening address this time is going
to be a virtual one given by the chief
executive of Hong Kong. and you know
he'll be you know officially presiding
over this even though he can't make it
in person but that's really really again
kind of a great signal that Hong Kong
really cares about this industry. So
>> those are some of the key things I'm
quite excited about within the um
conference itself. The other thing is
also as of this morning there's we just
counted over 310 side events that are
happening throughout the city.
>> Like that's an enormous number of side
events I have to say. And it's and it's
cool because again I mentioned earlier
like Hong Kong is home and I'm really
glad that people see this as like a
great product market fit to convene in
Hong Kong and to just really see Hong
Kong for all it has to offer, you know,
and I think that's going to be exciting
to see the city come alive. The energy
is going to be incredible and I'm really
excited about next week. I hope you are
too.
>> No, I am. I am. I'm partnering up with
you guys and I'll have a booth to do
interviews. Your lineup is one of the
best I've seen. Honestly, what does
success look like for you? Let's say,
you know, end end of this month and
we're celebrating Chinese New Year.
People are asking you how you feel about
this event. What do you hope you share
with people?
>> That's the reason why we have a vision
is, you know, did we successfully
execute on that vision? I think what I'd
love to be able to call success is that
one we were able to convene at scale
people from around the world at
consensus also to make sure that we've
delivered on this highquality content
does somebody have something substantive
novel and can they say it with authority
right and I think that's the kind of
measure that we want to be able to
deliver on that one I think the second
second part of that vision was you know
were we successful as a gateway to Asia
were people flying into here able to
really get an understanding of what's
happening across the region and
hopefully convincing them that they need
to pay attention just like we just
discussed, right? And the third part of
it was this idea of showcasing Hong
Kong. Were we successful in one helping
people understand what's happening with
the industry? And the second is was I
successful in getting people to fall in
love with Hong Kong and want to visit
again? Uh the answer hopefully is yes,
right? And I think that in itself is is
a great way for us to measure whether
we've been successful or not. The final
thing I'd say on it though is I believe
that consensus and it's kind of apt
right in the name itself is is uniquely
positioned in the industry to bring the
the whole kind of all the different
players together. And what I'm hoping
for is that it actually is a catalyst
for that ecosystem growth I talked
about, right? People actually finding
partners to work with, maybe new ones or
strengthening old ones. people finding
new ideas to work on, people
understanding what the key trends are,
and then hopefully starting to apply
either capital or energy and resources
to build towards it. Like to me, I feel
like it'd be it'd be nice to be able to
say we had a lot of people. It'd be
great to say we actually made a
difference in how like our industry
moves forward. And I think that's what I
would love to be able to look back and
be able to say we were able to help do
that for for the industry. Earlier you
mentioned a lot of countries see stable
coin as a store of value. I love
traveling and I've been to almost a
hundred countries and a lot of African
countries that I've been to, you know, I
actually have seen how they use their
currencies as souvenirs and it's fun for
the the visitors but it's such a painful
experience for the locals, right? So
there are a lot of things I think
crypto taught me or Bitcoin taught me
that I would like to translate that to
you know the audience and I think
it's very important to recognize that a
lot of you know parts of the world or
people are suffering or are struggling
because of financial education and a lot
of other reasons and I just want to you
know know your take on this subject.
>> I think definitely financial education
is an important thing. What's
interesting is the topic of blockchain
and bitcoin and crypto has really helped
to get people to rethink a lot of that
and really search you know a deeper
understanding like I would for example
say that most people including myself
when we first approached bitcoin we
never thought about you know what is
what is money like we you know I never
really thought deeply about how do I
think about money and fiat currencies
and like until I came across this and so
I think
>> this particular type of you know
technology and asset class is a great
way to kind of prop people down towards
understanding finance and and that
financial education path further. Right?
The second part of it is I do think that
this technology can provide greater
financial inclusion. Right? I think
there's an element of
easy access because you're now connected
to the internet that you are able to
have better access or access to better
financial um products and more more
scalable ones for that matter and I
think that's really really great and I
think there's certain parts of the world
that benefit more than others because
some places in the world don't have very
convenient traditional products right
and so therefore having this as an
alternative really makes a big
difference. I think the third piece and
this is something that I feel
particularly strong about in Hong Kong
is that when you think about how this
particular industry also is a great
opportunity for entrepreneurship.
>> One thing that I've noticed is that in
Hong Kong we have fantastic technical
universities. Um, yeah,
>> they have fantastic technical talent,
>> but we don't have very many of the web 2
technical businesses here, right? We
don't have, for example, a lot of
developers from the big web two internet
companies here. And so, people end up
leaving if you're pursuing something
that's more of a technical career or
whatever it might be. I think with with
with blockchain, with crypto, with web
3, because of how borderless it can be,
you know, depending on the application
you're in, it gives people an
opportunity to build global businesses
here in Hong Kong. I hope that means
that students that graduate from our
great university stay in Hong Kong and
build their, you know, businesses here.
That that's kind of my hope. Um, and by
bringing consensus over, I think the
idea is to create some level of
excitement for people to realize, oh,
this is serious. This is not just you
know a niche thing on the side. This
actually could make a big impact both in
terms of the city but also in terms of
building you know businesses that are
global
>> and changing their famil family's lives
and generations to come. I think that's
what people really want to do.
>> Yeah. No, completely.
>> That was very beautifully said. Thank
you, Michael. Um, I look forward to
seeing you in Hong Kong. And if people
are really interested in what we talked
about and want to check out Consensus,
you can check out the link down below.
Um, they gave me a discount code, so you
can go for cheap. Thank you, Michael,
and I'll see you again in Hong Kong, I
guess.
>> Thank you, Bonnie. It was great chatting
with you. I'll see you in Hong Kong.